<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://www.distributedsoup.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://www.distributedsoup.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-02-11T13:36:05-05:00</updated><id>https://www.distributedsoup.com/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Distributed Soup</title><subtitle>A blog full of cloudy thoughts.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">AI Capex, Cash-Flow Timing, and Why Markets Aren’t Celebrating Beats</title><link href="https://www.distributedsoup.com/blog/2026/02/08/ai-capex-cashflow-macro.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="AI Capex, Cash-Flow Timing, and Why Markets Aren’t Celebrating Beats" /><published>2026-02-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2026-02-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://www.distributedsoup.com/blog/2026/02/08/ai-capex-cashflow-macro</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.distributedsoup.com/blog/2026/02/08/ai-capex-cashflow-macro.html"><![CDATA[<p>Over the last earnings cycle, a familiar pattern emerged across large U.S. technology companies. Earnings beat expectations, revenue growth remained solid, guidance was generally positive, and yet equity market reactions were muted to even downright negative.</p>

<p>The dominant explanation circulating on LinkedIn, YouTube, and earnings recaps is that investors are growing uneasy about the scale and persistence of AI-driven capex. Across a small group of incumbents, annualized investment is now approaching or exceeding <strong>$600B</strong> on a run-rate basis, and markets are questioning whether or not this spending will earn an adequate return.</p>

<p>I started digging into this because the market reaction, and the explanations people were giving, didn’t sit right with me. It felt like everyone was pointing at “AI capex” in a vague way without actually explaining the mechanism.</p>

<p>The way I’ve come to think about it is less about AI “working” or “not working,” and more about timing. Large, front-loaded AI capex pulls cash forward and pushes free cash flow further out, at a moment when cash is expensive and risk capital is picky. In that setup, earnings beats still matter, but they don’t force a re-rating. Markets seem to be waiting for the cash to arrive.</p>

<h2 id="capital-expenditure-evidence-of-a-step-change">Capital Expenditure: Evidence of a Step-Change</h2>
<p>The current AI buildout represents a huge step-change in capital intensity across a small set of firms. To anchor the discussion, consider the scale:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Amazon.com, Inc.:</strong>
Capex accelerated sharply through FY2024–FY2025, with management signaling an annualized investment run-rate approaching <strong>$200B in FY2026</strong>, driven by data centers, custom silicon, logistics automation, and AI infrastructure.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Alphabet Inc.:</strong>
Capex increased from roughly <strong>$50B in 2024</strong> to approximately <strong>$90B in FY2025</strong>, with management guiding <strong>$175–185B for FY2026</strong> as AI infrastructure build-out continues.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Microsoft:</strong>
Capex approached <strong>$85–90B in FY2025</strong>, reflecting aggressive investment in cloud and AI capacity tied to Azure and Copilot. Microsoft reported <strong>$37.5B in Q2 FY2026 alone</strong>, putting it roughly on pace for <strong>~$145B in FY2026</strong>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Meta Platforms, Inc.:</strong>
Capex rose from roughly <strong>$40B in 2024</strong> to <strong>~$70B in 2025</strong>, with anticipated FY2026 capex in the <strong>$115–135B</strong> range as AI workloads and data center expansion continue.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>NVIDIA:</strong>
NVIDIA stands apart. It benefits directly from this capex wave without bearing it at the same scale. Its customers, hyperscalers, spend while NVIDIA monetizes quickly.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Taken together, these companies are committing <strong>well over half a trillion dollars</strong> in capital to AI-related infrastructure over a short window centered around FY2026. This alone is enough to change how markets think about valuation, even before asking whether this spending eventually pays off.</p>

<h2 id="earnings-great-valuations-muted---what-gives">Earnings Great, Valuations Muted - What Gives?</h2>
<p>So we know there is a huge step change in capex, but how did the companies do? In short, across the board, the tech firms delivered strong, double-digit revenue and net income growth. Performance was objectively good, no matter how you slice and dice it (YoY, QoQ, full year, month comparisons, etc). For reference, I highlighted the performance for the big tech firms below.</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Amazon.com, Inc.:</strong>
Reported Q4 2025 revenue of $213.4B, up 14% YoY. AWS (cloud) net sales grew 24% YoY with strong backlog growth (+40%). Net income increased 6% YoY to ~$21.2B for the quarter. <strong>Free cash flow fell despite operating cash flow growth due to heavy capex.</strong></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Alphabet Inc.:</strong>
Q4 2025 revenue grew 18% to ~$113.8B, net income rose ~30% YoY to ~$34.5B. Cloud revenue surged ~48% YoY. <strong>These strong results were accompanied by the unusually large capex guide.</strong></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Microsoft:</strong>
Q4 numbers showed double-digit net income growth, strong cloud performance, net income up ~23% YoY.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Meta Platforms, Inc.:</strong>
Q4 2025 revenue grew ~23.8% YoY with earnings also up ~9.3% during this period. Growth was tied to strong ad demand and AI features monetization.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>This makes the market reaction feel counterintuitive, until you separate the <strong>earnings</strong> from the <strong>cash flow</strong>. Think of earnings as just an accounting construct, whereas capex is your cash reality. It becomes a lot clearer when we understand how this capex hits the three financial statements: the <strong>income statement</strong>, the <strong>balance sheet</strong>, and the <strong>cash flow statement</strong>.</p>

<p>A useful grounding question is: <strong>How does capex flow through the balance sheet first, distort the income statement later, and only show up immediately in cash flow (which is what valuations actually care about)?</strong></p>

<p>To begin, all equity valuation collapses to the same framework.</p>

\[\text{Value} =  \sum \frac{\text{Future Free Cash Flow}_t}{(1+r)^t}\]

<p>What changed in this earnings cycle was the timing and visibility of their cash flows, not the long-term viability of these companies.</p>

<p>For the formula above, this means the inputs change. Front-loaded capex reduces free cash flow in the near term and shifts more of it into later years — increasing the effective <em>t</em> in the denominator. Because each future dollar is divided by (1+r)^t, cash that arrives later is worth materially less today. And the further out the cash flows sit, the more sensitive the valuation becomes to small changes in <em>r</em> or delays in execution.</p>

<p>This explains why earnings beats can coexist with valuation compression.</p>

<h2 id="where-the-adjustment-actually-happens">Where the Adjustment Actually Happens</h2>
<p>Capex affects the three financial statements very differently:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Income statement:</strong>
On the income statement, capex does not hit all at once. Instead, it’s capitalized on the balance sheet and expensed gradually through depreciation over time. That smooths reported earnings and keeps metrics like EPS and P/E ratios relatively stable in the near term. Revenue, margins, and operating profit can all look healthy even while the company is spending aggressively. Depreciation does eventually flow through EBIT, but it’s a slow, accounting-driven effect rather than a reflection of the immediate cash outlay. In short: the income statement mostly reflects execution, not cash strain.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Balance sheet:</strong>
The balance sheet is where capex shows up immediately as commitment. Cash goes down, and <strong>property, plant, and equipment (PP&amp;E)</strong> goes up by the same amount. This is the moment when capital becomes less reversible. Once cash is converted into data centers, custom silicon, or infrastructure, future returns depend on utilization and demand that hasn’t yet been proven. The company has effectively locked in a long-dated bet. The balance sheet captures what the company has committed to, not whether it will pay off.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Cash flow statement:</strong>
Capex is an immediate cash outlay that hits your cash flows in the near term.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

\[\text {Free Cash Flow} = \text {Operating Cash Flow} - \text{Capex}\]

<p>When capex ramps faster than operating cash flow, free cash flow compresses — even if earnings look strong. This doesn’t imply failure. It means cash returns are being pushed further out in time.</p>

<p>This is the statement valuations care about most, because equity value ultimately discounts future free cash flow, not reported earnings.</p>

<p>Valuation uses a required return (discount rate) which reflects the cost of capital and perceived risk. For a deeper breakdown of WACC and how it’s used in investment decisions, see my earlier post: Vibes vs. Numbers in Tech Investments <sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.</p>

<h2 id="why-re-rating-doesnt-happen-immediately">Why Re-Rating Doesn’t Happen Immediately</h2>
<p>A logical question to ask is: <strong>if capex eventually stabilizes, why not just reprice the companies now and get that stock price way up there?</strong></p>

<p>Backlogs, guidance, and early revenue signals matter, but they’re weaker evidence than sustained, bounded reinvestment and structurally higher free cash flow.</p>

<p>Investors want evidence that incremental AI revenue converts into high marginal cash flow, with capex intensity normalizing and free cash flow recovering structurally over multiple quarters.</p>

<p>By <strong>high marginal cash flow</strong>, I don’t mean high revenue growth or even high accounting margins. I mean that each additional dollar of AI-driven revenue generates a large amount of incremental free cash flow without requiring proportional reinvestment. In other words, revenue growth that scales on existing infrastructure rather than demanding another round of heavy capex. Markets are looking for evidence that AI workloads can move from capacity-building to utilization-driven economics, where incremental usage drops through to cash rather than pulling more spending forward.</p>

<p>This actually helps explain the divergent results within Big Tech.</p>
<ol>
  <li><strong>NVIDIA</strong> monetizes quickly and has short cash-flow duration. Its valuation remains near all-time highs without needing any heroic assumptions.</li>
  <li><strong>Meta</strong> reinvests heavily but its core ad engine throws off high-margin core cash flows. That cash subsidizes their AI investment, which keeps near-term cash flow resilient even as they increase capex.</li>
  <li><strong>Microsoft</strong> blends fast monetization (software, Copilot, enterprise contracts) with longer-dated infrastructure bets.</li>
  <li><strong>Amazon</strong> and <strong>Alphabet</strong> carry heavier, more irreversible infrastructure exposure. A larger share of their current cash is being pulled forward to fund assets with longer, less certain payback periods.</li>
</ol>

<p>Companies with more visible cash conversion retain premium valuations while those pushing cash further into the future see muted valuation response until the free cash flow proves itself.</p>

<p>Another way to frame this is as an AI investment loop. Capital is deployed first to build capacity, which enables usage, which then drives monetization, cash flow, and eventually reinvestment. Markets tend to re-rate after this loop visibly closes, not while it is still in progress. Today, most large incumbents are somewhere in the middle: capacity is expanding rapidly, usage is ramping, but durable free cash flow has yet to fully materialize. Until that final step becomes visible, valuation expansion remains deferred, even if earlier stages look strong.</p>

<h2 id="macro-factors-not-the-driver-but-reinforces-the-signal">Macro Factors: Not the Driver, but Reinforces the Signal</h2>
<p>All of this investment and waiting isn’t happening in a vacuum. The current AI capex cycle is unfolding against a macro backdrop that makes cash-flow timing matter more than usual.</p>

<p>At a high level, the Federal Reserve can influence financial conditions with two distinct levers:</p>
<ol>
  <li><strong>Policy rates</strong> (raise or lower the price of money)</li>
  <li><strong>Liquidity</strong> (increase or decrease the quantity of money in the system)</li>
</ol>

<p>These two are often conflated, but they don’t move together.</p>

<p>In recent years, rising unemployment (visible through rising jobless claims, softer job openings, moderating wage pressure) has acted like a short-term tailwind for equities. The logic seems straightforward (if not unjust): weaker labor data increases the likelihood of Fed rate cuts, pushing investors out of low-yielding safe assets like Treasuries and toward risk assets.</p>

<p>All else equal, lower rates reduce the discount applied to future cash flows, but this “all else equal” rarely holds true.</p>

<p>With inflation still sticky and fiscal deficits large, the Fed can cut short-term interest rates while still keeping liquidity constrained (not injecting the system with cash by performing QE). In other words, the price of money can fall even as the supply of risk capital stays limited. This is the environment we’re closer to today.</p>

<p>In that setup, borrowing costs may ease modestly, but the pool of capital stays selective, especially for long duration or uncertain returns. Without the liquidity tailwind from QE, markets are less willing to reward growth and earnings beats on their own.</p>

<h2 id="bonds-tell-the-same-story">Bonds Tell the Same Story</h2>
<p>The bond market reinforces the same cash-flow timing signal.</p>

<p>A key macro indicator is the <strong>yield curve</strong>, which shows the cost of borrowing across different maturities. Its shape conveys market expectations for growth, inflation, and cash flow timing.</p>

<p><strong>Short-term yields</strong> (3-month, 6-month, 1-year, 2-year Treasuries) are closely linked to Fed policy and reflect current inflation and funding conditions. <strong>Long-term yields</strong> (10-year, 20-year, 30-year Treasuries)  reflect expected growth, inflation and risk over time. These are less directly controlled by the Fed. When people say “yield curve” they are talking about yields across these maturities plotted together.</p>

<p>Usually, long-term yields exceed short-term yields because lending money for longer is riskier, so investors demand more return for inflation uncertainty, growth uncertainty and opportunity cost. The slope is positive.</p>

<p>Today, the curve is inverted, where short-term yields exceed long-term yields. This signals expectation of slower future growth and lower inflation relative to current conditions. It also signals that cash today is expensive while cash further in the future is discounted less aggressively.</p>

<p>A brief clarification, since bond pricing is often misunderstood: bonds pay a fixed coupon. When demand rises, bond prices increase but the coupon stays the same, so the yield falls. When demand weakens, prices fall and yields rise.</p>

<p>In an inverted yield curve, short-term yields are high because policy remains tight, while long-term yields are lower because markets expect slower growth and eventual rate cuts. Investors are effectively signaling that today’s cash is expensive, but future cash will be cheaper as policy eases.</p>

<p>For equities, the implication is consistent with the broader thesis. High near-term discount rates and constrained liquidity raise the opportunity cost of cash spent today. Companies investing heavily now for returns far in the future face skepticism, even if current earnings are strong, until cash-flow realization becomes more visible.</p>

<h2 id="the-connecting-thread">The Connecting Thread</h2>
<p>At this point, the pieces fit together. Large AI investments pull cash forward and push returns further out, increasing the duration of future free cash flows. In a different macro environment, markets might be willing to look through that timing shift.</p>

<p>Today’s backdrop is different. Elevated short-term rates, constrained liquidity, and an inverted yield curve all increase the opportunity cost of cash spent now and raise skepticism toward cash promised far in the future.</p>

<p>None of this means the AI investment cycle is broken. It may end up looking obvious in hindsight. But from where we are now, the market is placing more weight on realized cash flows than on forward narratives. Whether that happens smoothly or whether these investments overshoot before they pay off is still very much an open question.</p>

<h2 id="disclosure">Disclosure</h2>

<p>I hold a diversified equity portfolio primarily through broad market ETFs, with exposure to several of the companies discussed above. My investment horizon is long-term, and this analysis reflects my own thinking on capital allocation and cash-flow timing rather than any short-term trading view. This is not investment advice.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p><a href="https://distributedsoup.com/blog/2025/01/16/vibe-driven-tech-invest.html" target="_blank">Distributed Soup: Vibes vs. Numbers in Tech Investments</a> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="strategy" /><category term="technology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Over the last earnings cycle, a familiar pattern emerged across large U.S. technology companies. Earnings beat expectations, revenue growth remained solid, guidance was generally positive, and yet equity market reactions were muted to even downright negative.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What Survived Contact with Reality in 2025</title><link href="https://www.distributedsoup.com/blog/2025/12/28/contact-with-reality-2025.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What Survived Contact with Reality in 2025" /><published>2025-12-28T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-12-28T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://www.distributedsoup.com/blog/2025/12/28/contact-with-reality-2025</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.distributedsoup.com/blog/2025/12/28/contact-with-reality-2025.html"><![CDATA[<p>The past year was a pretty intense reset that forced me to stress-test my belief that advisory credibility can naturally preserve execution sharpness. I paused writing for a while to absorb what part of this actually held up and sit with what changed.</p>

<h2 id="execution-first-abstraction-later">Execution First, Abstraction Later</h2>
<p>I began my career with a heavy execution bias. Over the past few years in sales engineering, my work shifted closer to advisory conversations. That distance improved my leverage, but I wanted a real test to prove I could still ship the things I was recommending.</p>

<p>When I found an opportunity to perform rapid prototyping work at AWS, I jumped in with small team that moved fast, broke things, and delivered working protoypes. The pace stripped away abstractions quickly. Ideas that sounded clean in decks immediately ran into reality: security constraints, integration debt, unclear ownership, and edge cases that made AI systems behave unpredictably.</p>

<p>Most high-level conversations about AI and systems aren’t bottlenecked by interesting ideas (though shaping the approach is critical), but by unglamorous details required to actually make the systems work reliably.</p>

<p>This work was rewarding, but I also realized high-intensity prototyping, for me, is better as a powerful learning mode than as a place where I can sustain assymetric, long-term impact.</p>

<p>I continued pushing discomfort by taking on more interviewing roles and booting up an AWS Twitch program where I and a small team designed IoT systems at enterprise scale while answering live questions on the fly within our open-ended format.</p>

<h2 id="interviews-gaps-and-a-forcing-function">Interviews, Gaps, and a Forcing Function</h2>
<p>After that stretch, I entered a long, harrowing and humbling interview process that exposed real gaps but also rebuilt parts of my foundation.</p>

<p>I hadn’t interviewed seriously in over four years and assumed my experience could carry me. That was not the case. I flopped out of the gate, whiffing questions I should have cleanly handled. It was a reminder that I needed to be intentional about how I articulate things, not just understanding them. Interviewing skills can atrophy without deliberate practice.</p>

<p>One prompt was open-ended: <em>build something interesting with AI.</em></p>

<p>I started by building a functional chatbot combining Salesforce and Jira data, deployed via containerized MCP servers. I cut off the prototype once I hit the core use cases, and reasoned how this could be productionized (https://github.com/btang01/mcp-sf-jira).</p>

<p>After that, I slowed down and hand coded agentic loops from scratch to understand how schemas, memory, and control flow actually influence LLM behavior<br />
(https://github.com/btang01/claude-basics).</p>

<p>In one interview, I stumbled when asked to reason clearly about concurrency: how async systems behave, how work is scheduled, where coordination breaks down. It wasn’t a trick question but it exposed a gap between intuition and explanation. I also stumbled on system design and realized that I needed to reboot my design rigor.</p>

<p>Rather than hand-wave it away, I turned it into a forcing function. I put together a small reference repository (https://github.com/btang01/asyncio-basics) to make concurrency explicit instead of implicit. I walked through patterns end-to-end: sequential execution, task-based concurrency, gather, structured concurrency with TaskGroup (Python 3.11+), futures, and synchronization primitives like locks and semaphores.</p>

<p>Doing this forced me to slow down and answer questions that I’d previously glossed over including what concurrency is, what it looks like, common failure modes and why this matters so much for AI systems. Agents aren’t just interesting because of reasoning or tokens they generate - they run concurrently, share resources, fail independently and require coordination without collapsing into chaos.</p>

<p>In the end, this work mattered more than interviewing. It sharpened how I think about security, orchestration, reliability, and memory. This helped in two ways: I was able to help my customers navigate ambiguity in a new space, and now I know what frameworks like Strands SDK and ADK can effectively abstract versus what they don’t.</p>

<h2 id="moving-on">Moving On</h2>
<p>When the GCP Customer Engineer role came together, I took a brief pause. I kept things intentionally ambiguous so I could offload knowledge, close loops and leave cleanly. This period reminded me of how many people at AWS that I learned from, worked alongside, and genuinely respect.</p>

<p>When a travel window opened up, I had access to unstructured freedom for the first time in years with no destination constraints, timing or pace. Surprisingly, I found out that there’s always a reason not to go anywhere. Weather forecasts always felt bad, plans always felt suboptimal and waiting or even doing a staycation seemed more optimal. It surprised me that unlimited optionality actually created more unexpected friction.</p>

<p>In the end, I stopped optimizing, ignored the forecasts and booked a trip to Southeast Asia anyway. I chose motion over endless evaluation and was really happy with the result. This illustrated to me how freedom can just turn into inertia when every option is open and how progress only happens if you accept imperfect conditions and just choose to do something.</p>

<h2 id="wandering-then-hitting-limits">Wandering, Then Hitting Limits</h2>
<p>I spent time wandering without much agenda, walking streets and parks in Hanoi, watching daily routines unfold, eating street food, sitting longer than necessary. It wasn’t profound in a cinematic way and it was a reminder that most of life runs without demanding commentary or analysis.</p>

<p>That calm contrasted sharply with what followed. I rode motorcycles through Ha Giang and swam in waterfalls, which is a beautiful, chaotic experience. Being the “older guy” on the backpacking trail, singing karaoke badly, and playing pickup soccer in flip-flops all landed the same way: letting go of optimization and choosing participation instead.</p>

<p>After that I immersed myself in training Muay Thai hard twice a day, pushing myself and re-igniting old mechanics and my love for the sport.</p>

<p>When I came back, I didn’t really rest until a staph infection forced stillness. No lesson there beyond a simple one: limits exist whether or not you acknowledge them.</p>

<p>I’m excited about my new role and tried to hit the ground running, bringing together past experience but also trying to respect a new culture. My working definition of Googliness, for now, is simple: be intellectually honest, rigorous, and collaborative so we can build meaningful outcomes for customers.</p>

<h2 id="what-to-hit-in-2026">What to Hit in 2026</h2>
<p>There are a few things I want to put into motion next.</p>

<h3 id="agentic-systems-closer-to-reality">Agentic systems closer to reality</h3>

<p>I want to build beyond isolated Docker demos toward Kubernetes-based patterns—fleet-level services, hybrid deployments, and ADK-style frameworks that support long-running, resilient AI workloads without becoming fragile or prohibitively expensive.</p>

<h3 id="tackling-hidden-infrastructure-constraints">Tackling hidden infrastructure constraints</h3>

<p>Many of the customers I work with operate in the physical world. Cloud-only narratives break down when latency, bandwidth, autonomy, and resilience matter. Running intelligence closer to where the business operates forces clearer thinking about tradeoffs. Reality punishes hand-wavy diagrams, and tooling hasn’t fully caught up yet.</p>

<h3 id="finance-as-an-explanatory-layer">Finance as an Explanatory Layer</h3>
<p>I also want to spend more time writing about finance. Rather than hot takes, lean on first-principles thinking. Balance sheets, equity, leverage, cash flows, and how capital structure shapes which companies get to survive long enough for their ideas to matter. That kind of grounding feels increasingly necessary, especially in cycles dominated by memes, financial nihilism, and simplistic narratives.</p>

<h2 id="why-write">Why Write?</h2>
<p>I’m writing again because it helps me distinguish productive complexity from unnecessary friction. This blog is a way to finish thoughts instead of carrying them around half-formed. Writing is how I test whether an idea survives contact with reality. If it doesn’t, it probably shouldn’t guide decisions, whether it’s mine or anyone else’s.</p>

<style>
  ul, ol {
    margin-left: 1.2em;
    list-style: initial;
  }
</style>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflection" /><category term="career" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The past year was a pretty intense reset that forced me to stress-test my belief that advisory credibility can naturally preserve execution sharpness. I paused writing for a while to absorb what part of this actually held up and sit with what changed.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">US vs. China: Debt, Tariffs and the Race for Economic Dominance</title><link href="https://www.distributedsoup.com/blog/2025/05/11/us-china.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="US vs. China: Debt, Tariffs and the Race for Economic Dominance" /><published>2025-05-11T00:00:00-04:00</published><updated>2025-05-11T00:00:00-04:00</updated><id>https://www.distributedsoup.com/blog/2025/05/11/us-china</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.distributedsoup.com/blog/2025/05/11/us-china.html"><![CDATA[<p>If you’ve been following the headlines, you’ll be aware that the US and China appear to be locked in a struggle for global economic dominance. I started thinking more seriously about this after a one-sided debate with my dad (thanks, dad!). He rattled off stats and bold claims about the US and China, and I didn’t really push back because I wasn’t fully caught up on the details. I’m sure this situation is familiar to many readers.</p>

<p>Just to be clear, I’m not trying to take sides, be overly political, or make predictions. I simply wanted to research and share some observations. I think a lot of people feel the same way, confused by the constant headlines and wondering why the US government keeps talking about China while deploying tariffs, sanctions, and subsidies with such messy, reactive execution. I also want to dispel financial nihilism and explore things in more detail to more clearly understand half-truths vs. facts.</p>

<p>The short version: the US is trying to balance short-term protectionism with long-term reindustrialization, using tariffs and reshoring to buy time to rebuild domestic capabilities and reassert economic dominance.</p>

<p>There are a lot of nuances and caveats I want to unpack to help explain where things stand and get a whiff of what direction things are going, so let’s jump in.</p>

<h2 id="tariffs-buying-time-but-burning-bridges">Tariffs: Buying Time, But Burning Bridges</h2>

<p>The US has actually been deploying tariffs since 2018, starting with Trump’s steel and aluminum tariffs which were maintained under the Biden administration, which also added more against Chinese EVs, solar panels, and semiconductors. The idea seems pretty straightforward: slow China’s rise and protect US industries.</p>

<p>In the long term, tariffs erode US soft power and reserve currency dominance. They also motivate global trade partners to hedge against the US and explore non-dollar alternatives. Many are doing this already and we’ll get into why reserve currency dominance is so important in a bit.</p>

<h2 id="the-reshoring-and-rebuilding-trend">The Reshoring and Rebuilding Trend</h2>

<p>The US is also trying to reindustrialize. Both major parties in the US have taken actions in different ways to achieve this.</p>

<p>The CHIPS Act and Inflation Reduction Act (IRA) represent America’s carrot-based attempt to rebuild critical domestic manufacturing and supply chains. In 2023, the US committed over $280 billion in semiconductor incentives and clean energy support. The Trump administration of 2018-2020 used more of a stick-based approach to convince major manufacturers to onshore to the US… and that stick-based approach continues to this day through tariffs.</p>

<p>Additionally, recent data from the Federal Reserve Bank of St. Louis (aka FRED) indicates that total construction spending on manufacturing facilities in the U.S. reached a seasonally adjusted annual rate of $234.1 billion in March 2025, a significant increase from approximately $70 billion in early 2021. This surge suggests that the U.S. is making substantial investments in domestic manufacturing infrastructure, although it’s difficult to say whether or not the US can fully reverse decades of offshoring (<a href="https://fred.stlouisfed.org/series/TLMFGCONS">FRED, 2025</a>).</p>

<p>Even though major structural changes are in place to promote reshoring, execution always matters. We haven’t yet seen the actual impact on manufacturing output and employment. Furthermore, in economics class back in the day, the first thing we learned about was the benefits of comparative advantage, which reshoring/onshoring kind of flies in the face of, given all the specialization from the globalization that has already occurred.</p>

<p>It will be interesting to see how these long-term, strategic bets pay off.</p>

<h2 id="debt-and-the-trade-deficit-both-important-but-not-the-same">Debt and the Trade Deficit: Both Important, But not the Same</h2>

<p>Two other topics get thrown around a lot in the midst of these discussions: national debt and the trade deficit.</p>

<p>US <em>debt</em> now stands at over 123% of GDP (<a href="https://www.cbo.gov/publication/58946">CBO, 2024</a>). But America has always run large deficits, buffered by global demand for dollars. The US can still issue debt in USD and print money if needed, but uncontrolled debt can accelerate dedollarization (countries trying to move away from the dollar) which can negatively impact the reserve currency status and the ability for us to raise large amounts of money to fund our military, infrastructure, R&amp;D and social programs (… although I really don’t believe I’ll ever be able to withdraw from Social Security in my lifetime).</p>

<p>Britain is a cautionary tale, having lost reserve currency status after WWI and WWII due to debt and weakening economic power. The pound sterling devalued in 1949 and in 1967. The US emerged stronger from both crises, and the dollar was cemented as the global standard under the 1944 Bretton Woods agreement. Unique case, but 1967 wasn’t that long ago (<a href="https://distributedsoup.com/strategy/branding/2025/02/27/power-of-branding.html">Nike was born around then!</a>).</p>

<p>Another major topic of discussion is America’s persistent <em>trade deficit</em>. The US has run a trade deficit every year since 1975, with the gap widening dramatically after China joined the World Trade Organization in 2001 (<a href="https://www.census.gov/foreign-trade/statistics/historical/">U.S. Census Bureau, 2025</a>).</p>

<p>In 2024, the US trade deficit stood at over $140.5B, and if you strip out services and just talk about goods trade deficit, it was at $1T. While this is often portrayed as a weakness, it’s also been a structural feature of our dollar based system. The US consumes more than it produces, exporting dollars to the world, and in return foreign governments and investors recycle those dollars into US assets like Treasury bonds. This “exorbitant privilege” keeps US borrowing costs lower than they would otherwise be. The downside is something we see today and what our government has been trying to address: long term decline of domestic manufacturing, which explains the more recently intense push toward tariffs, industrial policy, and reshoring.</p>

<p>The combination of high debt and persistent trade deficits has become a key talking point for political leaders. They see the decline of US manufacturing and the massive trade imbalance (especially with China) as signs of weakness and vulnerability. Trump’s approach has been to use tariffs as both a negotiation tool and a blunt-force attempt to reverse these trends and bring manufacturing back to American soil.</p>

<p>In many ways, the America’s economy is trapped in a strange cycle. It runs trade deficits to satisfy global demand for dollars, which allows the US government to borrow cheaply and fund its domestic spending. Trump’s argument seems to be that this bargain is no longer working for average Americans, as jobs have been outsourced and local industries have been gutted.</p>

<p>I want to clarify that I don’t agree with the execution or the economic theory of benefits of tariffs. Again, in economics 101, we learned that tariffs aren’t actually good for consumers since you’re really just passing the costs of goods over to the consumers. Other critics also point out that trying to reverse this system too abruptly could destabilize the very global dollar dominance that makes US debt sustainable. In an inflationary environment, this can make things even worse.</p>

<p>This tension explains why trade deficits and debt are so politically charged. It also explains why tariffs, reshoring, and “America First” policies are back in the conversation.</p>

<h2 id="a-note-on-the-middle-class">A Note on the Middle Class</h2>

<p>It’s worth mentioning that a big reason why all of this even matters is the impact on people’s lives. The long-term trends of globalization and offshoring have been good for consumers (lower prices), investors, and high-skill knowledge workers, but have been pretty brutal for large parts of the traditional American middle class.</p>

<p>Wages stagnated for many non-college-educated workers, which partly explains the political energy behind tariffs and reshoring efforts. A recent report from Pew Research Center shows the middle class has shrunk from 61% of US adults in 1971 to 50% in 2023. Some of that is positive (many households moved upward into upper-income brackets), but inequality has widened, and the lower-income share also grew slightly (<a href="https://www.pewresearch.org/race-and-ethnicity/2024/05/31/the-state-of-the-american-middle-class/">Pew Research, 2024</a>). The US economy increasingly looks like an hourglass: a bigger upper class, a squeezed middle, and a persistent lower tier.</p>

<h2 id="reserve-currency">Reserve Currency</h2>

<p>I mentioned earlier that the US has a special power with reserve currency dominance and I’ll jump into that now.</p>

<p>The dollar’s role as the world’s reserve currency gives the US enormous leverage. Today, about 58% of global reserves are held in USD (down from 71% in 1999) (<a href="https://data.imf.org/?sk=E6A5F467-C14B-4AA8-9F6D-5A09EC4E62A4">IMF COFER, 2024</a>), and roughly 88% of global foreign exchange trades involve dollars (<a href="https://www.bis.org/statistics/rpfx22.htm">BIS, 2022</a>). Commodities, oil, and global trade flows run through USD, making US Treasuries the world’s safest and most liquid asset.</p>

<p>Issuing debt in its own currency gives the US the unique ability to borrow cheaply, run persistent government fiscal deficits, and fund military and social programs without risking a currency collapse. When global markets panic, they run to dollar assets. We saw this during the COVID crisis and again after Russia’s invasion of Ukraine.</p>

<p>In contrast, countries like Argentina and Turkey must borrow in foreign currencies or offer much higher yields to attract investors. This reflects their higher default risk and economic instability and severely limits their financial flexibility.</p>

<h2 id="cracks-in-the-dollar">Cracks in the Dollar</h2>

<p>There are some signs of dedollarization that puts this reserve currency strength at risk. Russia, China, India, and Brazil are diversifying into gold, yuan, euros, and other assets (<a href="https://www.gold.org/goldhub/research">World Gold Council, 2024</a>). China and Russia are settling energy trades in yuan and rubles. China and Brazil partially conduct trade in yuan. India and Russia have trialed non-dollar oil trades. Central banks globally are quietly stockpiling gold as a hedge.</p>

<p>China and older BRICS nations—Brazil, Russia, India, and South Africa—have been pushing for non-dollar trade to reduce reliance on the US financial system. Asia’s Regional Comprehensive Economic Partnership (RCEP), which includes China but not the US, also illustrates how global trade is starting to fragment.</p>

<p>Still, it doesn’t seem like there is a clear alternative. The euro remains structurally weak given that there isn’t a unified federal budget or fiscal policy, creating constant tension and risk of fragmentation. The Chinese RMB is non-convertible, with tight capital controls maintained by the People’s Bank of China. Gold is impractical for modern global commerce as a medium of exchange: you can’t easily move it quickly, it can’t earn interest, and it doesn’t do any productive work. So it seems that, for now, the US Treasury market remains a safe haven.</p>

<p>That said, recent moves in long-term Treasury yields show that markets are starting to price in a little more uncertainty. This doesn’t mean people think the US will outright default. The US issues debt in dollars and can always print more if needed. But rising deficits, unpredictable fiscal policies, inflation volatility, and occasional political debt ceiling drama have all raised what economists call the “term premium.” Investors want a bit more compensation for holding long-term US debt because the future looks messier than it used to. Still, I wouldn’t say the US is going to default.</p>

<h2 id="the-scorecard-us-vs-china">The Scorecard: US vs. China</h2>

<p>The US still represents roughly 25% of global GDP and leads in AI, biotech, intellectual property, and finance. Deep capital markets, global acceptance, and legal stability anchor the dollar’s appeal. But government debt is high, and poorly executed negotiation moves hurt the credibility angle, and some regions are already diversifying out of caution.</p>

<p>China holds the advantage in other areas. China leads in global GDP by purchasing power (PPP, $30.3T vs. $25.5T for the US) (<a href="https://databankfiles.worldbank.org/public/ddpext_download/GDP_PPP.pdf">World Bank, 2024</a>). China also dominates global manufacturing with 41% share compared to the US’s 13%. Additionally, China also holds over $3.2 trillion in FX reserves and maintains strong productivity and labor force growth.</p>

<p>China’s weaknesses include a debt-to-GDP ratio of over 335% when including corporate and government debt, plus strict capital controls that limit RMB convertibility. Its highly centralized decision-making structure also creates risks of inefficiency, resource misallocation, and overproduction bubbles.</p>

<p>A caveat about this perceived weakness is that most of China’s debt is owed internally so that gives the government a large amount of control over creditors and debt restructuring. They are not at the mercy of foreign investors that might cause a sudden run. They also use much of the debt on infrastructure, housing and manufacturing, real assets that can be productive for the country.</p>

<h2 id="both-sides-playing-for-time-is-it-working">Both Sides Playing for Time: Is It Working?</h2>

<p>From what I understand, the US is attempting to slow down China’s rise in some critical areas, but some data indicates that China continues to find ways to advance.</p>

<p>The US is targeting tariffs and restrictions at critical tech and energy sectors while allowing lower-risk trade to continue. The goal is to buy time to reshore industries and strengthen domestic supply chains, all the while keeping some of the benefits of comparative advantage.</p>

<p>Similarly, China is following a dual circulation model: internally focusing on supply chain independence (semiconductors, EVs, AI, energy, pharma) while externally expanding markets into Southeast Asia, Latin America, Africa, and the Middle East.</p>

<p>In EVs, China has surged ahead. BYD, Xpeng, and Nio overtook Tesla in global deliveries in late 2024 (<a href="https://www.counterpointresearch.com/">Counterpoint Research, 2025</a>). China’s EV ecosystem is vertically integrated since they own battery, motor, and rare earth supply chains.</p>

<p>In AI, US export controls slowed Chinese access to NVIDIA’s H100/A100 chips, but China is pivoting fast with domestic players like Huawei’s Ascend and Biren chips. China’s huge internal dataset and demand also give it an edge for training large models (<a href="https://www.scmp.com/">SCMP, 2025</a>).</p>

<h2 id="the-next-510-years-managing-contradictions">The Next 5–10 Years: Managing Contradictions</h2>

<p>On a personal note, I still remember my time at Tufts (many years ago) when the prevailing narrative was that China’s economy, while growing rapidly, was still distant second to the US. It’s been fascinating to watch China burst onto the stage during the 2008 Olympics, and since then, how explosive growth has propelled China to near-parity with countries that had a century-long head start, lifting 800 million people out of poverty (<a href="https://www.worldbank.org/en/news/press-release/2022/04/01/lifting-800-million-people-out-of-poverty-new-report-looks-at-lessons-from-china-s-experience">World Bank, 2022</a>).</p>

<p>I used to hope that the global system might evolve into something closer to the liberal view of shared growth, cooperation, and stability under global norms. I even took a class where I and my fellow bright-eyed students debated global harmony. It took one game of simulated <em>Diplomacy</em> to see how quickly things can devolve into betrayals, shifting alliances, and an “all against all” mentality.</p>

<p>The modern world increasingly resembles what realists predicted: a fragmented, multipolar system of rivalry, with middle powers hedging to protect their own interests. But, I still hold the hope that there is a future of peace and prosperity for people in all countries, harmony even amongst the major powers.</p>

<p>Neither country has a clear blueprint to “win.” China risks stifling innovation through over-control and over-planning. The US risks damaging its alliances and punishing its own consumers by leaning too hard on unpredictable tariffs and export controls. Major players like Japan, South Korea, Germany, and the ASEAN nations are already carefully balancing their relationships with both sides.</p>

<p>The eventual winner may not be the one with the biggest GDP, but the one that best manages its internal contradictions, adapts to shifting global leanings, and maintains resilience in the long term. For now, the U.S. has bought itself time. Whether it can convert that into sustainable advantage is unclear.</p>

<p>I realize that ultimately, a lot of my views are from a Western-centric lens, and limited to what I think and have read. I’d love to hear other thoughts. Do you believe the U.S. can maintain its lead? Will China’s strategy ultimately succeed? Are we headed for a long-term balance of competing powers?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="economics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[If you’ve been following the headlines, you’ll be aware that the US and China appear to be locked in a struggle for global economic dominance. I started thinking more seriously about this after a one-sided debate with my dad (thanks, dad!). He rattled off stats and bold claims about the US and China, and I didn’t really push back because I wasn’t fully caught up on the details. I’m sure this situation is familiar to many readers.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Branding</title><link href="https://www.distributedsoup.com/blog/2025/02/27/power-of-branding.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Branding" /><published>2025-02-27T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-02-27T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://www.distributedsoup.com/blog/2025/02/27/power-of-branding</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.distributedsoup.com/blog/2025/02/27/power-of-branding.html"><![CDATA[<p>To me, branding has always felt like a fuzzy, overhyped concept. Marketers and other consumers obsess over branding, but it’s something I never really cared for. However, two amazing books, that I recently read back-to-back, changed my perspective quite a bit.</p>

<p>One was <em>Shoe Dog</em>, a memoir by Phil Knight<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, who tells the story of Nike’s suprisingly scrappy beginnings and the other was a gift from my partner called <em>This Is Not a T-Shirt</em>, by Bobby Hundreds<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>, who recalls how he built The Hundreds from a backyard operation into a streetwear company that made its voice heard, and endures in a challenging market.</p>

<p>Other than a feel-good corporate underdog story and a light, surface-level intro into the fashion world, I didn’t expect much. However, I walked away with a deeper appreciation for branding–not just as a cynical way of selling overpriced products to easily-influenced people, but as a component of strategy that pulls together psychology, storytelling and business. In a way, creating a brand does make the world a bit more interesting (if not better) - it’s about building emotional connections, creating communities, and turning simple stuff into cultural icons that can inspire people.</p>

<p>While Nike and The Hundreds are super different (one is a global sportswear titan and the other is a grassroots streetwear label), they shared common threads when it comes to developing a brand as a moat. And if you’re a business, you should care about this since it is such a powerful driver of pricing and margins.</p>

<p>Based on their stories, they each created this moat through a combination of hustle, credibility and community.</p>

<p>Phil Knight built his brand by embedding himself in the hardcore running world, innovating to improve performance and securing athletes that would make Nike an aspirational brand. Bobby Hundreds, on the other hand, built The Hundreds by embedding himself in street culture, curating careful collaborations and consciously making customers feel like part of a movement.</p>

<p>They both took unconventional (and sometimes questionable) steps to deliver value and reach success, but did so with a lot of admirable heart and courage. Somewhere between Nike’s “Just Do It” philosophy and <em>The Hundreds’</em> underground vibe is a formula for building a long-lasting brand.</p>

<p>So what did I learn? Let’s jump in.</p>

<h2 id="nike-three-little-but-powerful-words"><strong>Nike: Three Little, but Powerful Words</strong></h2>
<p>Before I read <em>Shoe Dog</em>, I actually thought Nike had been around forever. Nike has existed from before my birth and naturally I should feel that way. But Knight’s story shattered that illusion, revealing that Nike didn’t start as the empire that we know today (this thought also made me consider how short life is, but considering mortality is a post for another day).</p>

<p>Nike actually started as a bluff. Straight out of business school, Knight flew to Japan and pitched himself as the US distributor for Onitsuka running shoes - the only problem was that “Blue Ribbon Sports”, a name he made up on the spot, didn’t exist as a real company.</p>

<p>That early lie became a catalyst to what Nike has become today. Knight had to earn his brand equity through vision and a willingness to hustle, but balance that with the ability to deliver results. He created the foundation one pair of shoes at a time - importing product and selling directly to athletes at local races, track meets, run clubs, building a base of customers that would eventually influence a larger audience.</p>

<p>Alongside this, his early co-founder Bill Bowerman, a running coach, pushed the boundaries of product innovation, continuing to build credibility among serious runners. He tried all types of crazy experiments in search of a better shoe. At one pivotal point, he poured rubber into a waffle iron to create the first waffle sole, a major breakthrough for high-performance running shoes. Together, they engineered and marketed performance gear for serious athletes, strengthening that aspect of their brand identity.</p>

<p>To reinforce this identity, Bowerman also used his influence as a coach to put their shoes on elite runners. Their big wins included convincing Steve Prefontaine, a running legend, to wear their shoes. Their athlete-first strategy would be solidified, evolving into iconic moves like signing Michael Jordan and launching Air Jordans, then immortalizing this rebel, competitive spirit into the slogan “Just Do It” and inspiring people to push themselves to the limits, much like the athletes they look up to.</p>

<p>However, even a brand like Nike isn’t invincible - if you’ve been paying attention, Nike’s recent headwinds can be traced back to their aggressive direct-to-consumer (DTC) push that began during COVID. While it did boost margins in the short run, this move hurt their relationships with traditional retail partners.</p>

<p>In “This Is Not a T-Shirt”, Bobby mentions that retailers aren’t just distribution channels, but partners that co-sign your product, serve as brand tastemakers that lend credibility and reach to customers. Retailers aren’t just sales channels, but they are also cultural validators - the specialty stores not only sell your product, but also legitimize it in the eyes of consumers.</p>

<p>Besides losing the co-sign effect, there are other operational considerations like having to shoulder more of the supply-chain burdens of returns, shipping, customer service, etc. but we can leave the operational topic for another post.</p>

<p>I actually saw this scenario play out locally in Boston. The last time I walked into a Marathon Sports store, a gold standard of a runner’s shoe store, there wasn’t a Nike Swoosh to be found - only Hokas, ONs, Brooks, Saucony, and Asics. After having read <em>Shoe Dog</em> and really understanding the origin and story of Nike, feeling Phil Knight’s emotion and passion for running, it actually made me a bit sad. At that moment, it felt like Nike’s magic had faded, straying from its roots and, in a way, ghosting the running community that once defined the company.</p>

<p>Nike has felt the real effects of this in slipping margins and flattening revenue growth<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>. It’s a cautionary tale that even a brand as strong as Nike can drift if it loses sight of the communities and relationships that made it that strong in the first place. Will focusing on hardcore running bring back tremendous growth? Not necessarily, since Nike is a much larger and more complex company than it was when it started - but there is something important about finding a strong, authentic core that inspires people and draws them to the brand.</p>

<p>With the return of the previous CEO, Elliot Hill, and a promise to get back to core sports (running and training), retail partnerships and product innovation, I am hopeful for Nike’s future prospects. The path back will require some humility (backtracking on key decisions) and strategy to get there.</p>

<h2 id="the-hundreds-creating-a-culture-of-credibility-through-community"><strong>The Hundreds: Creating a Culture of Credibility Through Community</strong></h2>
<p>On a smaller scale, The Hundreds continues to survive in the streetwear space (fashion is still a topic that I’m still trying to “get”). Bobby Hundreds built his brand on skate, graffiti and punk culture, focusing on “People Over Product”. It’s less about volume and more about creating communities - people who are willing to queue up for drops and come to the stores even if the products are available online. At its peak, people did this because of the power of the brand’s story - they wanted to be a part of it.</p>

<p>However, the community didn’t appear overnight. Bobby manufactured this momentum and legitimacy before it took off organically.</p>

<p>One of the stories that stood out to me in <em>This Is Not a T-Shirt</em> is how Bobby launched in his first two retail accounts. He convinced an influential boutique to carry a small set of his T-shirts, then used this placement to influence another retailer to stock his T-shirts as well. After doing this, he orchestrated an immediate sell-out by dialing in and asking about the product, as well as getting his friends and family to buy them all. He made The Hundreds “hot”. While the sales were staged, he capitalized on this short term success.</p>

<p>Unlike Knight’s bluff, Bobby’s move was about jump-starting demand, not fabricating a company. Bobby doubled down on the initial spark by building a real community behind this company.</p>

<p>Bobby recognized the dangers of leaning too hard on a single trend. When one of his icons, the Adam Bomb, blew up in a good way, he was careful to not tie everything to that character, even though that’s what partners and customers demanded. He knew that the streetwear world is fickle, and that overexposure can kill a brand.</p>

<p>He was also extremely creative and adopted an air of exclusivity early on. While many other small shops would fight to try to gain the attention of vendors at expos and trade shows, he intentionally kept his product covered up and kicked his feet back to create a sense of rarity to drive up interest. It didn’t work overnight but he committed to this approach (along his other decisions and moves) to drive long term demand.</p>

<p>Consistent with these moves, Bobby’s brand building strategy involved partnering with artists, respected labels and becoming more of a cultural curator. Rather than leaning on collaborations as gimmicks, he treated them as an extension of his brand’s values. While each new partnership brought in new audiences and fresh designs, he reinforced The Hundreds’ authenticity in the streetwear world.</p>

<p>Bobby recognized that credibility is the currency for subcultures like skate and punk, so any misstep - a tone-deaf collaboration, making a brand-damaging move by selling in the wrong stores, could undo his work. His thoughtful partnerships helped The Hundreds grow while many others failed.</p>

<p>Another notable story was Bobby’s retelling of the infamous Gap logo rebrand fiasco - the company panicked and backpedaled when a small set of customers criticized the change. Bobby likened this to a friend who constantly agrees with anything you say and avoids conflict at all cost, desperate to fit in. It’s like a friend who isn’t willing to show you who they are. When a brand acts like this, it can feel flat and uncommitted, losing the respect and loyalty of the audience, generating indifference. Strong brands don’t just chase the audience’s approval, but shapes the culture, and tries to find something that the customer doesn’t even know they want yet.</p>

<p>As the years have passed, The Hundreds, like streetwear itself seems to be at a crossroads. Today, with its products in more mainstream outlets like Zumiez, there is chatter that the brand is straying outside its original promise. Streetwear once thrived on rebellion, but in the latest hype cycle, mainstream brands appropriated its aesthetics, blurring streetwear’s cultural edge. At the high end, streetwear merged with high fashion and became a way for people to show off their wealth, not to express themselves. At the low end, everyone who has a TikTok account and a interest in streetwear saturated the market with similar-looking styles. Now that the hype has died down somewhat, some argue that streetwear has returned to its subculture roots, but that would mean that the market is smaller, fragmented - it seems harder to build a behemoth out of this.</p>

<p>Despite its past success and influential role in millenial streetwear culture, there are signs that the Hundreds might be struggling in the current cycle. Forums, Discord channels and comment boards are quiet or shut down. It’s flagship stores have closed as well. Bobby even briefly alluded to this tension in his book, noting that a lot of core, millenial customers had started aging out (great, now I’m thinking about mortality again). While the brand outlasted many competitors with its diverse operations like printing for other companies and building a strong cut-and-sew process, the Hundreds’ journey is a reminder that building a brand isn’t a once-and-done thing.</p>

<p>The Hundreds had a brilliant run and Bobby seems aware of this need for constant evolution, finding a balance between staying true to your roots and adapting to a changing world.</p>

<p>It may no longer dominate the streetwear conversation as it once did, but its legacy—and its potential to reinvent itself keeps me hopeful, even if it ends up re-emerging as something else.</p>

<h2 id="from-a-feeling-to-finance-quantifying-brand-power"><strong>From a Feeling to Finance: Quantifying Brand Power</strong></h2>
<p>Brand is a power that lasts because customers feel something about a business that rises above a product’s specifications or price tags. Once people have locked into this feeling, it secures a strong moat and significantly impacts financial performance. Generally, a brand’s true value lies in its ability to change consumer behavior - it can increase revenues, improve your profit margins and even reduce costs of capital<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>.</p>

<p>But a moat by itself isn’t worth much if you can’t see it in the numbers. If you zoom right into what a brand does, it lets you charge more (pricing power) and also to sell more (volume) because your buyers believe that you have a business that is special. The proof is in the cash flows, margins, and market share of big brands like Coca-cola, Advil, etc. versus generics.</p>

<p>However, brand value isn’t static and businesses need to continually invest, cultivate, and keep a pulse on the power of the brand or else it can slowly degrade over time due to neglect, cultural shifts, or negative associations.</p>

<p>Doing this turns our intangible perceptions into valuable financial gains and provides a powerful moat to protect the company’s market position.</p>

<h2 id="the-fine-line-between-hustle-and-hustler"><strong>The Fine Line Between Hustle and Hustler</strong></h2>
<p>The whole other layer to this whole branding puzzle is how you jump start this machine in the first place and overcome the “why should anyone care about us?” phase.</p>

<p>Nike did this by bluffing (but delivering) its way into legitimacy, The Hundreds staged its first sell-outs.</p>

<p>However, the hacks really only work if you can back these actions up with substance. Though Knight initially bluffed, he developed a powerful distribution network to move his product, and developed relationships and communities to sustain the business. Bobby Hundreds built a loyal community after the initial placement into key retailers and expanded his capabilities to provide more diverse and better products to market.</p>

<p>Similarly, we see this with tech companies like Uber that subsidized drivers and riders in every new city until it established its network effects (amongst other a bit questionable methods for growth hacking - a lot of interesting anecdotes can be found in <em>The Cold Start Problem</em> by Andrew Chen <sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup>). Uber kept its riders after initial growth-hacky acquisition because it delivered on excellent customer experience, surpassing taxis in convenience.</p>

<p>I was surprised to find how creating a legitimate company can operate more in the gray area than I expected. The way Knight described his accounts payable and accounts receivable processes sounded borderline like a Ponzi scheme at times.</p>

<p>The key thing here is that they were able to deliver on their promises, not just try to sustain a manipulative move. This raises an ethical concern though… Phil Knight and Bobby Hundreds ultimately built the companies they claimed to have but there is some survivorship bias… for every Nike and Hundreds there are hundreds of Theranos and FTXs that are just smoke and mirrors and collapse into chaos.</p>

<p>Does the end result–success–validate the bluff? It’s tempting to say yes because after all, Nike became a global powerhouse. This cold start aspect is a dangerous game, rewarding boldness but only if you are able to back it up quickly - if you fail to do this, you become just another con artist.</p>

<h2 id="wrapping-up-strategy-and-soul"><strong>Wrapping Up: Strategy and Soul</strong></h2>
<p>What I learned is that a brand is more than a logo or a flashy campaign. A good brand transforms an everyday purchase into an emotional connection, a feeling that brings consumers back and compels you to participate in its story. Stories like Nike and The Hundreds show this at different scales but demonstrate how this intangible preference can fuel powerful business returns - they also reveal how walking this tightrope is treacherous and how many have failed in this arena. Even today, Nike and the Hundreds both have to fight to stay relevant in a dynamic environment.</p>

<p>So… what does it mean if you’re working in solutions architecture, sales or consulting? At first, you might not think building a brand is something that matters to you, but I think it’s quite useful to consider.</p>

<p>Brand power extends beyond sneakers and streetwear. It’s actually embedded in every decision customers make–even in B2B and enterprise sales (I recognize this is starting to sound like a LinkedIn-bro post now – I can already see the title: “What Streetwear Taught Me About B2B Sales”– but I’m going to continue down this line of thinking).</p>

<p>Consider how clients respond to names like McKinsey, Bain or BCG (MBB, the Big Three) when trying to develop a strategic plan. You could argue that industry experts in other consulting companies could deliver similar recommendations, but there’s a brand weight behind the recommendation, a co-sign that carries huge influence.</p>

<p>Similarly, in tech, if you’re a Solutions Architect like me, building on AWS, you have the advantage of leaning on a strong brand in cloud computing. So many large customers are <em>powered by AWS</em> or <em>built on AWS</em> and these references carry weight, credibility, and trust. Customers co-publishing success stories is similar in some ways to a sneaker being sold in a top-tier running store, an implicit co-sign.</p>

<p>In both sales and consulting, a brand can act as a sort of borrowed trust. When you walk in, customers might not know you, but they have an expectation based on the company behind you. That brand sets the tone before you even start talking. This opens doors and you can align with that tone, using testimonials, known partners, industry standards to make a point. This puts you in a position to add value and even extend the reach of this borrowed trust. It’s important to remember that overpromising and underdelivering will quickly erode that trust.</p>

<p>Phil Knight walked the line and built Nike. Elizabeth Holmes and Sam Bankman Fried walked the same line, committed fraud and paid a steep price. In the end, people might not remember the bluff… but they will remember whether or not you delivered results.</p>

<p>So, think about how branding applies to what you do, or even how you might be building a brand today. Think long term and about the story you have to tell and how you can consistently deliver on that promise, so that in the long term, you keep those doors open and can create something amazing. So… just do it, but do it thoughtfully and with purpose.</p>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Shoe-Dog-Memoir-Creator-Nike-ebook/dp/B0176M1A44" target="_blank">Shoe Dog - Phil Knight</a> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/This-Not-T-Shirt-Community-Streetwear/dp/0374275793" target="_blank">This Is Not a T-Shirt: A Brand, a Culture, a Community–a Life in Streetwear - Bobby Hundreds</a> <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p><a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2024-12-19/nike-shows-improvement-in-new-ceo-s-first-earnings-report" target="_blank">Bloomberg: Nike CEO Turnaround Rests on Unraveling Predecessor Mistakes</a> <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p><a href="https://aswathdamodaran.blogspot.com/2024/10/just-do-it-brand-name-lessons-from.html" target="_blank">Just do it! Brand Name Lessons from Nike’s Troubles - Aswath Damodaran</a> <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:5">
      <p><a href="https://www.amazon.com/Cold-Start-Problem-Andrew-Chen/dp/0062969749/ref=sr_1_1?dib=eyJ2IjoiMSJ9.QIC2IHf1mU8SFPqOeB-72_wCEc601oI5uy0UJII4dzPHVM98qvIyYExlgrzEXSHvQbMeIH4sD5mwPm4NZ0WKpeUoO68iNXeFdH3ETbUCmHSjmlW_K4hgdRxAwOOmBgRcDF7L117kuRK0PK2kvUbkG4cEUopIKrvxFxTj0q28LkISX17amG-36EG7bULXtA-ztKb3Po8U2onZuExcnvYfghiqtcxbfAMWeIWpKaZQ_50.XDJjuo1Ags5YRK4W49AyMS7C8R_BMFaBU1IPyWiSAeE&amp;dib_tag=se&amp;hvadid=496337412370&amp;hvdev=c&amp;hvlocphy=9001989&amp;hvnetw=g&amp;hvqmt=e&amp;hvrand=8880861981827279526&amp;hvtargid=kwd-1164758991056&amp;hydadcr=27886_10744793&amp;keywords=the+cold+start+problem&amp;mcid=cf720515ce8c391ea758c44a1beee66a&amp;qid=1740596764&amp;sr=8-1" target="_blank">The Cold Start Problem - Andrew Chen</a> <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="strategy" /><category term="branding" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[To me, branding has always felt like a fuzzy, overhyped concept. Marketers and other consumers obsess over branding, but it’s something I never really cared for. However, two amazing books, that I recently read back-to-back, changed my perspective quite a bit.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Vibes vs. Numbers in Tech Investments</title><link href="https://www.distributedsoup.com/blog/2025/01/16/vibe-driven-tech-invest.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vibes vs. Numbers in Tech Investments" /><published>2025-01-16T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-01-16T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://www.distributedsoup.com/blog/2025/01/16/vibe-driven-tech-invest</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.distributedsoup.com/blog/2025/01/16/vibe-driven-tech-invest.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="introduction"><strong>Introduction</strong></h2>
<p>Over the past 14 years, I’ve collaborated with at least a dozen multi-billion dollar organizations in a wide array of industries<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. One recurrent theme stands out: tech project investments often feels more vibes-driven than being grounded in rigorous financial analysis.</p>

<p>This post will explore why I think it happens, why this is a problem, and offer an approach that tries to account for the idiosyncracies unique to tech and business - to balance intuition and analytics to drive better decisions.</p>

<p>Since this is potentially a controversial topic and I run the risk of upsetting both technical and business-oriented people (maybe even artists as well), I’ll caveat that all the opinions in this blog are my personal observation and don’t reflect the views of my employer. Let’s jump in…</p>

<h2 id="why-vibes-driven-investments-are-common"><strong>Why Vibes-driven Investments are Common</strong></h2>
<p>It’s not that calculations are completely absent, but arguments for projects typically go like this: “We’ll increase revenue by releasing features faster, innovate more, boost customer experience, and cut costs by improving productivity and reducing overhead.”</p>

<p>There are also a wide array of tools that can pull extensive metadata right out of your data centers and run some calculations that help you estimate how much you might save by getting out of pricy licenses or right-sizing your compute resources (based on industry benchmarks). There are cloud calculators that can incorporate assumptions and nail down estimated costs of each particular service down to thousandths (and beyond) of decimal places.</p>

<p>Though the claims are valid and the data is detailed, these components are usually only brought together for the initial pitch and lack the structure you need to measure long-term value or guide strategy.</p>

<p>I think there are 3 main reasons for this:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Complexity and Uncertainty Inherent in Technology:</strong>
Real-world IT systems and modern applications are extraordinarily complex - it’s tough to precisely model the cost and value of every single existing and future component (since the data usually isn’t collected in an easily consumable way), let alone dial in every risk and benefit of actually executing the project. A McKinsey study found that 70% of digital transformations fail<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>, and I’ve been around long enough to see what a monumental effort it takes to prevent that failure. The consequences of breezing over execution can be total failure and a leadership overhaul<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>. On top of all of this, tech moves fast: innovation cycles and competitive pressures cause leaders to make decisions under tight time constraints - there is a high risk of being disrupted or counter-positioned so leaders also need to rely on a certain amount of vision and intuition to quickly make a decision. In the time it takes to conduct a thorough due diligence analysis of thousands of workloads, you might miss a market window and the juice (the results of the analysis) may not be worth that squeeze. As an SA, one of the most asked questions I get is: what are other similar customers doing and how is it going? It’s a good question, and an attempt at shortcutting this painful process.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Vendor-driven Projects:</strong> Many projects I see are selected based on whichever vendor can pitch most persuasively. This is a bit of a roll of the dice since a lot hinges on the vendor’s ability to sell and if it is selected based on pure cost-competitiveness, presents risks. A good partner should be able to explain assumptions clearly, does the hard work to collaborate with customers to align to strategy and create as rigorous a model as possible. Without this type of expectation (a kind of negotiation really) it’s difficult to arrive at a realistic solution and you risk overpromised benefits and underdelivered results. During my time in consulting, I saw plenty of pre-sales dreams that turned into implementation nightmares - it was not uncommon for me to be the third or later wave in a revolving door of consultants trying desperately to right the ship.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Fear of Accountability:</strong> Given the dangers inherent in 1 and 2, vendors live on a knife edge of trying to win the project but also trying to avoid committing to concrete projections since they could be held accountable for unpredictable outcomes and factors that are hard to measure to begin with. The pain the customers and vendors are trying to avoid is finger-pointing if the project fails to deliver on those promises. The result is a lot of ambiguity and an environment more full of vibes than locked-in numbers (besides available budget) and this can limit future innovation, investments, and a strong foundation to pivot from when strategies evolve.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Deciding to live with these reasons and accepting this ambiguity means that your organization doesn’t improve its decision-making mechanism when you <strong>inevitably have to make another tech investment in the future</strong>.</p>

<h2 id="financial-modeling-basics"><strong>Financial Modeling Basics</strong></h2>
<p>In contrast, when a company generally makes an investment, they apply some financial tools or metrics to appraise whether or not something is worth pursuing. From buying a soccer team (don’t do this<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup>), to purchasing a factory or acquiring another company, this is typically what is done. Here’s a crash course from a business standpoint (and across my interactions from developers to managers to directors to VPs to the C-suite, something I’ve surprisingly never seen). Could be that I’m too low on the totem pole though.</p>

<p>The first basic concepts are using <strong>cost of equity</strong> and <strong>cost of debt</strong> to come up with a <strong>Weighted Average Cost of Capital (WACC)</strong>. What the company needs to return from an investment to satisfy shareholders (those that bought shares of your company) is <strong>cost of equity</strong> and what they need to satisfy debtholders (those who lent you money) is <strong>cost of debt</strong>. The company should use both of those to calculate <strong>WACC</strong> or the hurdle rate, which is the average rate that the company should earn on any new project to figure out if you are adding or destroying value. You can factor in taxes to make this even more accurate.</p>

\[WACC = \frac{E}{V} \cdot Re + \frac{D}{V} \cdot Rd \cdot (1 - Tc)\]

<p>Where:</p>

<ul>
  <li>\(E\): Market value of equity</li>
  <li>\(D\): Market value of debt</li>
  <li>\(V = E + D\): Total value of capital (equity + debt)</li>
  <li>\(Re\): Cost of equity</li>
  <li>\(Rd\): Cost of debt</li>
  <li>\(Tc\): Corporate tax rate</li>
</ul>

<p>And voilà - in this simple example you have <strong>WACC</strong>, your hurdle rate, or minimum acceptable rate of return. Typically any project that can return more than this WACC percentage number should create value for the company.</p>

<p>WACC will be the basis of your <strong>discount rate</strong> used in calculating the value of your tech investment.</p>

<p>If you are a finance nerd, you might adjust this <strong>discount rate</strong> if the risk is higher (add a risk premium!) or lower (discount this further!), but if you have a standard WACC as the benchmark, you can just use that as a baseline. However, this is just one piece of your investment puzzle.</p>

<p>So what about the project itself? To understand the value, you can figure out the expected yearly <strong>cash flows</strong> of the project, then discount them with a <strong>Net Present Value (NPV)</strong> calculation.</p>

<p>To get the <strong>cash flows</strong>, this is where you make a lot of assumptions about how much revenue you would generate (and how) as well as what costs you would reduce. Combine that altogether to estimate the yearly <strong>cash flows</strong> of your project.</p>

<p>You can then apply the <strong>NPV</strong> formula to figure out what all those cash flows are worth in today’s dollars over a period of time. You have to remember to factor in your up-front investment, and if you want to be really specific, bake in growth assumptions during the initial year(s) and the terminal value near the end of the period of your project (if it makes sense to do so).</p>

<p>The basic Net Present Value (NPV) formula is:</p>

\[NPV = I_0 + \sum_{t=0}^{n} \frac{C_t}{(1 + r)^t}\]

<p>Where:</p>
<ul>
  <li>\(I_0\) = Initial investment amount at \(t=0\)</li>
  <li>\(C_t\) = Cash flow at time \(t\)</li>
  <li>\(r\) = Discount rate</li>
  <li>\(t\) = Time period</li>
  <li>\(n\) = Total number of periods</li>
</ul>

<p>After you set up your NPV formula, you still have to figure out if the <strong>Internal Rate of Return</strong> (<strong>IRR</strong>, the rate that makes the NPV = 0) is greater than or less than your <strong>WACC</strong>.</p>

<ul>
  <li>If <strong>IRR &gt; WACC</strong>, then your project beats the company’s average <strong>cost of capital</strong> (other way to call <strong>WACC</strong>) so it makes sense to go ahead.</li>
  <li>If <strong>IRR &lt; WACC</strong>, your project will probably not make sense, unless there is some other intangible strategic goal that you haven’t factored into your calculation.</li>
</ul>

<p>By the way, trying to set <strong>NPV = 0</strong> just means that you imply that the cash inflow and outflows will be equal. So that would represent the project’s intrinsic rate of return.</p>

<p>Additionally, you might want to calculate some top-level numbers like <strong>Return on Investment (ROI)</strong> over a certain period of time and understand when your investment breaks even. At this point you’re slicing and dicing similar concepts.</p>

<p>Clearly there are a lot of assumptions involved, especially due to the complexity/uniqueness of tech projects, so in the next section, I’ll propose a balanced, step-by-step analysis approach.</p>

<p>All of this to say… pure business analyses is not sufficient - if you treat technology projects and teams as widgets, you ignore factors like tech debt, execution risk, and have a glaring hole that can lead to failure, regardless of your model. Not treating tech debt seriously often comes because you are paralyzed by how much to invest in fixing things (seen as low value) versus releasing new features to the point where your operations slows (or as I have seen) grinds to a halt. There’s a great article about the importance of tackling debt<sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup> and worth a discussion, but outside the scope of this current post.</p>

<p>And when it comes to just building these financial models, there are a lot of pitfalls<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup> you need to avoid and ultimately you still need to weave this all together in a narrative that is built on an informed vision and intuition<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup>.</p>

<h2 id="balancing-analysis-and-vibes-for-tech-decisions"><strong>Balancing Analysis and Vibes for Tech Decisions</strong></h2>
<p>So if the soft tech estimate is not enough and the pure business calculation is too in-the-weeds and falls apart under the weight of assumptions, what can we do?</p>

<p>Ultimately, the core question when it comes to valuation is: <strong>do I invest or not?</strong> And this is based on the question: <strong>if I invest, what do I expect to return from this investment?</strong></p>

<p>And in addition to just the pure valuation, you also have to take into account whether this <strong>aligns with a good strategy</strong><sup id="fnref:8"><a href="#fn:8" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">8</a></sup>. What problem will this solve for me at an organizational level - and based on competitive dynamics, will this help me in the long run? For instance, how might it reduce my costs, grow my revenue, improve my moat?</p>

<p>Many pitches fall short of addressing these fundamental questions. The costs are too broadly assumed, revenue gains are glossed over and the ties to strategy are vague. While it’s reasonable to expect that the immediate benefits are hard to measure, I do agree with the sentiment that, ultimately, “if there are no benefits, then the investment is not strategic”.<sup id="fnref:9"><a href="#fn:9" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">9</a></sup></p>

<h2 id="the-idea-of-option-value-over-npv"><strong>The Idea of Option Value Over NPV</strong></h2>

<p>I came across an article by Rita McGrath, a Columbia Business school professor, who advocates for an approach where you focus on <strong>option value</strong><sup id="fnref:10"><a href="#fn:10" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">10</a></sup> and flexibility instead of trying to project cash flows too far out in the future right off the bat. She calls out the shortcomings of NPV analysis in tech projects which can be too rigid since it can omit uncertainty and strategic potential.</p>

<p>What she calls out actually resonates with the way I’ve seen my colleagues and go-to-market teams position tech projects, which is to start with a pilot, which reduces risk by capping your initial investment losses, then using your learnings to make subsequent decisions. Additionally, Rita applies the concept of <strong>Expected Value (EV)</strong> to assign probabilities to those decisions.</p>

<p>The key principles are to:</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Start small and scale</strong> - pilot smaller projects with a targeted set of personas, scope, and well defined goals to demonstrate value and then expand to other use cases or teams</li>
  <li><strong>Measure leading indicators of success</strong> - non-financial metrics as proxy to show that value: this could be adoption rates, increased customer retention, reduced churn, higher Net Promoter Scores (NPS) or Customer Satisfaction Scores (CSAT) that can be tied to the project, etc.</li>
  <li><strong>Prioritize investments that allow you to adapt</strong> - aim solutions that allow you scale and pivot</li>
</ol>

<p>After the pilot phase, you should be in a better place to take a stab at the cash flow projections. Although leaning on EV is great for flexibility, I still think the rigor of NPV analysis can be effectively combined with this approach to validate a project’s long term potential and to  create a data-backed narrative to hold it all together. You can continue to scale incrementally to minimize risks, creating insights along the way to validate your approach. And I think the only way you can consider your potential options over time as you scale up is to model what you know, so you need this foundation and data collection process.</p>

<h2 id="example-applying-real-options-thinking-to-a-cloud-migration"><strong>Example: Applying Real Options Thinking to a Cloud Migration</strong></h2>
<p>Bringing these complex ideas in a simple example helps, so suppose your company is thinking about migrating to the cloud.</p>

<p>The first step might be to consider a small pilot project - for example, spending $200k to migrate a business critical application to the cloud. You might have to do a bit of bottoms-up estimation to break down cost of database workloads, application hosting costs, etc. to try to estimate value.</p>

<p>You can try to lean on industry analyses as benchmarks from sources like the IDC<sup id="fnref:11"><a href="#fn:11" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">11</a></sup> - for instance, 10-15% revenue uplift and 30% faster time-to-market from cloud migrations is nice to know. Benchmarks can show that you are moving in the right direction, but it’s still important to put a plan in place to track data points and detect improvements because <strong>you are not necessarily the industry average</strong>. From the top-down you use the industry benchmarks and tools that lean on those benchmarks to serve as a sanity check<sup id="fnref:12"><a href="#fn:12" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">12</a></sup>.</p>

<p>The pilot phase mitigates risks by letting you test without committing your full budget up front. During this time, you can assess the app performance in the cloud and see how your leading <strong>Key Performance Indicators (KPIs)</strong> are doing. You can use this information to extrapolate the long term benefits and find concrete ways to determine a mid-term and long-term NPV.</p>

<p>Data points that inform the initial model include the cost of running the on-premises data center (DC). For example, $500,000 per year in energy, maintenance, staffing, depreciation costs. Perhaps there is a hardware refresh of about $1M every 5 years or so.</p>

<p>Understand the cash flows from the project by using the savings between on-premises cost and the annual cloud cost. The first cut at this may be tough but should include factors like:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Initial migration costs for year 0</li>
  <li>Cost of cloud cost growth in the near term and long-term (terminal).</li>
  <li>Consistent efficiency savings (X% in tasks and calculate savings in $/hour of salary)</li>
  <li>Potential revenue generating tasks</li>
</ul>

<p>After the pilot stage (and really at every subsequent stage), you have 3 different decision points/options:</p>
<ol>
  <li><strong>Scale</strong> out your initiative: pick another group, business unit, etc. to expand (assign some cash flow value to this)</li>
  <li><strong>Adjust</strong> the approach: you determine that you could benefit from taking a different approach to the migration<sup id="fnref:13"><a href="#fn:13" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">13</a></sup> and this has a different assigned cash flow value</li>
  <li><strong>Terminate</strong> the project: in this case, you’ve capped your initial investment losses.</li>
</ol>

<p>You can use the <strong>real options</strong> approach using probabilities to calculate an Expected Value (EV). The benefit of this is that you can use this knowledge in the future for more decisions.</p>

<p>Example:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Success Probability could be 60%</li>
  <li>Partial Success Probability could be 30% and you learn how to adjust</li>
  <li>Failure probability might be 10%</li>
</ul>

<p>So:</p>

\[EV = (60\% \times $240,000) + (30\% \times $100,000) + (10\% \times (-$200,000))\]

<p>Simplifying:</p>

\[EV = $144,000 + $30,000 - $20,000 = $154,000\]

<p>You have the ability to expand or adjust based on the information. As part of this exercise, you’ll likely identify areas where you do not have the data, but then this is time to get those processes and tools in place.</p>

<p>This approach balances NPV and EV with some flexibility. It helps you manage risks and also better link the project to your business goals and this staged investment is based on data which cap your downside risks. Beyond the pure financials, the pilot and scale approach gives you the opportunity to learn, to build your capabilities and create a baseline to scale sustainably in the future. You now have the opportunity to make informed decisions based on probabilities instead of rigid projects so that you have room to maneuver.</p>

<p>As you get better data using all the tools and metrics at your disposal, construct the NPV and the narrative to create a better tie to long-term value.</p>

<h2 id="closing-thoughts"><strong>Closing Thoughts</strong></h2>
<p>Customers struggle with performing their own exhaustive modeling (IRR, NPV, ROI) in-house because it takes a lot of effort, time, requires deep-expertise, and might still fall short of the accuracy that they want, versus taking a quick cut at some estimates, looking at the benchmarks and then just “doing the thing”. The nature of tech means that some drawbacks of pure NPV analysis<sup id="fnref:14"><a href="#fn:14" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">14</a></sup> are amplified. I’ll admit that what I propose seems tough to do and I don’t blame anyone for not trying.</p>

<p>For truly big acquisitions (valued in the billions), companies will bring in a third party to conduct the transaction (valuation, due diligence, arbitration/negotiation, etc). However, even tech projects can benefit from a similar type of discipline. By blending strategic alignment, all the analytical tools at your disposal, and incorporating flexibility with real options thinking, I think there is a way forward to minimize uncertainty and to realize measurable value for tech projects.</p>

<p>I believe that there is a sweet spot that exists where you can combine strategic thinking, financial rigor and flexibility through real options thinking. If you start with pilots, track carefully designed metrics, and iterate based on information and insights you pick up along the way, you can set up a roadmap towards sustainable success. For additional information, there’s a great resource on Educause that goes through a similar framework in great detail<sup id="fnref:15"><a href="#fn:15" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">15</a></sup>.</p>

<p>What are your experiences with tech investments? Do you rely more on intuition, financial models or mix both?</p>

<style>
  ul, ol {
    margin-left: 1.2em;
    list-style: initial;
  }
</style>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
  <ol>
    <li id="fn:1">
      <p><em>If you really want to know: automotive, industrial manufacturing, e-commerce, consumer electronics, aviation, state entities, non-profits, education, healthcare (admittedly, some of these industries overlap)</em> <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:2">
      <p><a href="https://www.mckinsey.com/capabilities/transformation/our-insights/why-do-most-transformations-fail-a-conversation-with-harry-robinson" target="_blank">McKinsey: Why do most transformations fail?</a> <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:3">
      <p><a href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2025-01-13/sonos-ceo-patrick-spence-leaving-after-failed-app-revamp-led-to-customer-revolt" target="_blank">Bloomberg: Sonos CEO Leaving After Failed App Revamp Led to Customer Revolt</a> <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:4">
      <p><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=s7N-xXGgdE4" target="_blank">Modern MBA: Why Football is Bad Business</a> <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:5">
      <p><a href="https://www.mckinsey.com/capabilities/mckinsey-digital/our-insights/breaking-technical-debts-vicious-cycle-to-modernize-your-business" target="_blank">McKinsey: Breaking Tech Debt’s Vicious Cycle</a> <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:6">
      <p><a href="https://aswathdamodaran.blogspot.com/2015/02/dcf-myth-1-if-you-have-ddiscount-rate.html" target="_blank">Aswath Damodaran: Myth 1 - DCF If you Have a Discount Rate</a> <a href="#fnref:6" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:7">
      <p><a href="https://aswathdamodaran.blogspot.com/2015/08/dcf-myth-2-dcf-is-exercise-in-modeling.html" target="_blank">Aswath Damodaran: Myth 2 - DCF is Exercise in Modeling</a> <a href="#fnref:7" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:8">
      <p><a href="https://distributedsoup.com/strategy/2025/01/01/strategy1.html" target="_blank">DistributedSoup: What is Strategy?</a> <a href="#fnref:8" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:9">
      <p><a href="https://www.cfo.com/news/when-projects-have-a-zero-or-negative-npv/660037/" target="_blank">CFO.com: When Projects Have a Zero or Negative NPV </a> <a href="#fnref:9" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:10">
      <p><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/npv-doesnt-work-risky-high-potential-projects-heres-better-mcgrath/" target="_blank">Rita McGrath: NPV Doesn’t Work… Here’s a better approach</a> <a href="#fnref:10" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:11">
      <p><a href="https://pages.awscloud.com/rs/112-TZM-766/images/IDC-Whitepaper-The-Business-Value-of-AWS-Global.pdf" target="_blank">IDC Whitepaper: The Business Value of AWS</a> <a href="#fnref:11" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:12">
      <p><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/mt/create-a-data-driven-migration-business-case-using-aws-cloud-value-framework/" target="_blank">AWS: Create a Data-driven migration business case</a> <a href="#fnref:12" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:13">
      <p><a href="https://aws.amazon.com/blogs/enterprise-strategy/6-strategies-for-migrating-applications-to-the-cloud/" target="_blank">AWS: 6 Strategies for Migrating Applications to the Cloud</a> <a href="#fnref:13" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:14">
      <p><a href="https://www.investopedia.com/ask/answers/06/npvdisadvantages.asp" target="_blank">Investopedia: NPV Disadvantages</a> <a href="#fnref:14" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
    <li id="fn:15">
      <p><a href="https://library.educause.edu/-/media/files/library/2014/7/erb1408-pdf.pdf" target="_blank">Educause: IT Infrastructure Projects a Framework for Analysis</a> <a href="#fnref:15" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p>
    </li>
  </ol>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="strategy" /><category term="technology" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Introduction Over the past 14 years, I’ve collaborated with at least a dozen multi-billion dollar organizations in a wide array of industries1. One recurrent theme stands out: tech project investments often feels more vibes-driven than being grounded in rigorous financial analysis. If you really want to know: automotive, industrial manufacturing, e-commerce, consumer electronics, aviation, state entities, non-profits, education, healthcare (admittedly, some of these industries overlap) &#8617;]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflecting on Strategy as a Solutions Architect</title><link href="https://www.distributedsoup.com/blog/2025/01/01/strategy1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflecting on Strategy as a Solutions Architect" /><published>2025-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2025-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://www.distributedsoup.com/blog/2025/01/01/strategy1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.distributedsoup.com/blog/2025/01/01/strategy1.html"><![CDATA[<p>Since my last post about 4 years ago, the world has changed quite a bit: an AI revolution has taken a grip over the world’s collective imagination and the terrible impact of COVID is now viewed (by most) as a quaint speedbump in our rearview, and the average 30-year fixed rate that bottomed at about 3% in 2021 is now closer to 7% today (the debate of the Fed funds rate vs. mortgage rates is actually quite a <a href="https://aswathdamodaran.blogspot.com/2024/09/fed-up-with-fed-talk-central-banks.html">complicated topic</a>). Despite all these macro-level events, I think a good strategy to help navigate all this craziness as a company or even as an individual still remains very much the same.</p>

<p>Bringing all this back to the focus of this blog (tech and business) - what is strategy? Strategy often gets thrown around loosely and the meaning can get watered down - most of us use strategy as a way to sprinkle “important” dust on an initiative or idea.</p>

<p>This makes sense though. Who doesn’t want their idea to be important, strategic, etc? There are various definitions of strategy and I have a humble view of it that helps me conceptualize it and turn it into something that I can use day-to-day.</p>

<p>2 books stand out as being particularly good at describing strategy and developing a good one: “Good Strategy, Bad Strategy” by Richard Rumelt and “7 Powers: The Foundations of Business Strategy” by Hamilton Helmer.</p>

<p>I mostly follow Rumelt, who defines a good strategy in 3 parts - it has to <strong>diagnose</strong> a key kernel of a problem, have a <strong>guiding policy</strong> to address this issue and then <strong>coherent actions</strong> that support the execution of the strategy. This is great because it is simple to follow and understand, but also requires critical thinking in defining the problem. Not only that, but by thinking about it in this way, you can think about how an organization might have a strategy and then mirror that to individual business units and then further tie operations and information technology strategy to coordinate lower-level (in no way am I being derogatory - I live here), critical functions.</p>

<p>For example, an ecommerce company predicts that in the next 5 years, becoming a more “green” company will be key to remaining competitive, growing the customer base, and deflecting the costly regulatory penalties that will be coming their way. There is a <strong>diagnosis</strong> that the brand is strong but not recognized as environmentally friendly. At an org-level they may have a <strong>guiding policy</strong> to shift towards becoming more environmentally-friendly lifestyle brand over the next 5 years. Their <strong>coherent actions</strong> might be to:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Diversify into sustainable product categories</li>
  <li>Prioritize environmentally responsible sourcing and production</li>
  <li>Engage in community outreach and education on sustainability to grow that part of the brand</li>
</ol>

<p>You can see how this is a bit more detailed than a lofty vision but still remains understandable at the company/org-level. Additionally, these ideas all tie together cohesively without too much messy overlap (MECE, but you can fight me on this).</p>

<p>By breaking it down in this simple way, a business unit’s (let’s say the kitchen and home products group) strategy could be that they <strong>diagnose</strong> that despite the growing demand for sustainable home products, they have limited offerings in this space. Their <strong>guiding policy</strong>, after careful analysis , is to shoot for 15% market share in sustainable home products with a 10% increase in revenue over the next 3 years. Their <strong>coherent actions</strong> would be to:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Create innovative and env-friendly kitchen and bath products</li>
  <li>Engage with influencers for promotion and education</li>
  <li>Launch sustainability-based loyalty programs</li>
</ol>

<p>This brings us down to the ground of the technology group. Sometimes when I’m in the weeds working on automation, building DevOps cultures, or even straight up designing a highly available and scalable architecture, it makes sense to step back to see how this helps in the big picture… with this approach to strategy, I think it helps.</p>

<p>For example, the IT strategy could <strong>diagnose</strong> the current issue as: the current digital platform doesn’t convey any sustainability messaging and lacks advanced features that modern eco-conscious consumers care about. Your <strong>guiding policy</strong> as an IT org might be to upgrade the digital platforms to underscore the sustainability commitment and enhance the customer experience with that context. <strong>Coherent actions</strong> to support this policy could be:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Re-invent the e-commerce experiences by showing metrics like scores related to sustainability (i.e. carbon footprint, water saved, etc.), and introducing augmented reality features (that could cut down on physical returns, waste, etc.)</li>
  <li>Design a mobile app centered on education, product sustainability, recycling opportunities - to support a closed-loop green business</li>
  <li>Focus on instrumenting manufacturing and supply chain operations to further improve demand forecase and reduce waste, and pass these benefits on to the consumers</li>
</ol>

<p>The world’s messy and not perfect, but trying to tie the little actions that you see on the ground to the big picture helps you stay focused working on the highest priority tasks. There are numerous contradictions and complicated relationships you have to navigate to prove that you are on the right course. For example, Aswath Damodaran did quite a bit of analysis on actual benefits and impacts of ESG and you could look at some data and see this as an economically challenging initiative - <a href="https://aswathdamodaran.blogspot.com/2024/11/the-siren-song-of-sustainability.html" target="_blank">The Siren Song of Sustainability</a>.</p>

<p>Helmer supplements this overall definition of strategy with more rigor. His math makes my head spin a bit but makes his logic pretty sound. From my understanding, Helmer defines strategy as <strong>a route to sustaining an advantage in an attractive market</strong> - and to make it easier to remember, he consolidates this to 7 powers. A lot of the topics revolve around competition thinking about your power relative to others, but business is a bit of a war so I can roll with that.</p>

<ol>
  <li><strong>Scale Economies</strong> - how getting bigger gives you more advantage in lower per unit costs, can be a barrier for others</li>
  <li><strong>Network Economies</strong> - how a platform becomes more valuable, powerful as it gets bigger</li>
  <li><strong>Counterpositioning</strong> - how your position against a competitor can be good or bad</li>
  <li><strong>Switching Costs</strong> - how making it difficult to switch to a competitor can be an advantage</li>
  <li><strong>Branding</strong> - how branding leads to increased willingness to pay, protects your margins</li>
  <li><strong>Cornered Resources</strong> - how getting access to key resources can box others out</li>
  <li><strong>Process Power</strong> - how operational excellence yields better products and cost profiles, making it difficult to imitate</li>
</ol>

<p>A lot of this has been mentioned before in Michael Porter’s “5 Forces” book, but I think the examples provided and the accompanying calculations all cement these ideas very well. I basically try to frame my thoughts around Rumelt and then try to see if there are any elements from the 7 Powers that could be applicable. For example, if I tackle operations well and secure limited, cost-effective green raw materials, I could be cornering a resource. And as my operations get better and better, I could be pushing my advantage - by the time regulatory penalties kick in (probably one of the major economic factors for going green), I would be way ahead of the competition.</p>

<p>As a Solutions Architect, a technical role, you might wonder how any of this helps. It helps a lot actually. When you work with your account team, a key part of the work (at least at AWS) involves writing an account plan. This plan benefits from understanding strategy - otherwise, you’re listing and pursuing an endless number of opportunities and workstreams that may either diverge from what is important to the customer or may not be helpful at all. It’s hard to make an impact. Thinking critically about what strategy for your customer could look like helps you connect all the dots and create a narrative that can bring all of this messy, chaotic work together - it helps you and the team better look around the corner and advise the customer. At the very least, it gives you a point of view that you can iteratively refine rather than poking around in the dark.</p>

<p>All of this sounds fluffy so in future posts I’d like to dig into some of the analytical work that I try to conduct to pressure test interesting hypotheses and ideas.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="strategy" /><category term="general" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Since my last post about 4 years ago, the world has changed quite a bit: an AI revolution has taken a grip over the world’s collective imagination and the terrible impact of COVID is now viewed (by most) as a quaint speedbump in our rearview, and the average 30-year fixed rate that bottomed at about 3% in 2021 is now closer to 7% today (the debate of the Fed funds rate vs. mortgage rates is actually quite a complicated topic). Despite all these macro-level events, I think a good strategy to help navigate all this craziness as a company or even as an individual still remains very much the same.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First Post</title><link href="https://www.distributedsoup.com/blog/2021/02/15/hello-world.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First Post" /><published>2021-02-15T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2021-02-15T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://www.distributedsoup.com/blog/2021/02/15/hello-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://www.distributedsoup.com/blog/2021/02/15/hello-world.html"><![CDATA[<p>As of Feb 2021, approximately 7 million blog posts are created every day. 1 more blog shouldn’t hurt. There are quite a few thoughts floating around in my head, and a blog seems like a good way to organize ideas and share insights. Think of it like a filing cabinet for my brainspace. Likely, all the topics I mention will fall into two buckets:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Technology - cloud tech, security, coding, distributed computing, microservices, industry trends (hop on board the hype train)</li>
  <li>Business - productivity, consulting, current events, industry trends</li>
</ol>

<p>Having lived most of my career at the intersection of business and technology, I have seen how the two have more closely coincided in a way that ultimately makes my list above non-MECE. I’d like to peel back the layers of buzzwords like BlockchainAIMachineLearningCryptoIoT, “digital transformation”, etc. and observe them with a skeptical eye from both lenses - the geeky in-depth understanding of what these things are and how they work, as well as the meaning of these concepts from a business sense.</p>

<p>Selfishly, this blog is also a side project that will allow me to experiment with a variety of technologies. I’ll keep readers up to date with what’s going on there, but again, that’s probably mostly for my own benefit.</p>

<p>Behind the scenes, this site is a static web page hosted on AWS Simple Storage Service (S3). The content I write is written to a GitHub repository, compiled and served up using Jekyll and deployed using a Continuous Integration/Delivery process run with CircleCI. All of these services at this point are free (including the static website hosting) and I don’t have to maintain any infrastructure.</p>

<p>If I had a mission statement for this blog it would be this: maintain the blog as cheaply as possible with as little effort as possible so that I can focus on content.</p>

<p>There are still some basic things that need work. I’m new to Jekyll so right now I have to search how to do every little thing, which is kind of painful, but pretty much par for the course when learning new tools.</p>

<p>For example, I don’t have a sidebar for archives and recent posts which would be very nice. I also don’t have any pictures and I’m using the barebones template I took from Jekyll (called minima). Additionally, I’d like to incorporate Disquss comments and Google Analytics into this site, but I’m not exactly sure where to start.</p>

<p>I started documenting my trials and tribulations for getting this site set up, but since it’s so specific to my machine and circumstances, I figure it’s kind of pointless to post this in favor of headier, more fun topics. Onwards.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflection" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As of Feb 2021, approximately 7 million blog posts are created every day. 1 more blog shouldn’t hurt. There are quite a few thoughts floating around in my head, and a blog seems like a good way to organize ideas and share insights. Think of it like a filing cabinet for my brainspace. Likely, all the topics I mention will fall into two buckets: Technology - cloud tech, security, coding, distributed computing, microservices, industry trends (hop on board the hype train) Business - productivity, consulting, current events, industry trends]]></summary></entry></feed>